<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd" packageId="urn:uuid:b17bec41-e427-4792-bf3a-f83a5516e465" system="knb"><dataset><title>NCEAS Data Science Training Exercise 1 - Reformatted Permafrost Dataset</title><creator id="2079433426979388"><individualName><givenName>Scott</givenName><surName>Mortensen</surName></individualName><organizationName>NCEAS</organizationName><positionName>Data Science Fellow</positionName></creator><creator id="8076187248035321"><individualName><givenName>Michael</givenName><surName>Loranty</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="6115685896023560"><individualName><givenName>Wil</givenName><surName>Lieberman-Cribbin</surName></individualName></creator><pubDate>2016-09-14</pubDate><abstract><para>In arctic tundra and boreal forest ecosystems vegetation structural and functional influences on the surface energy balance can strongly influence permafrost soil temperatures. As such, vegetation changes will likely play an important role in permafrost soil carbon dynamics and associated climate feedbacks. Processes that lead to changes in vegetation, such as wildfire or ecosystem responses to rising temperatures, are of critical importance to understanding the impacts of arctic and boreal ecosystems on future climate. Yet these processes vary within and between ecosystems and this variability has not been systematically characterized across the arctic-boreal region. Here we quantify the distribution of vegetation productivity trends, wildfire, and near-surface soil carbon, by vegetation type, across the zones of continuous and discontinuous permafrost. Siberian larch forests contain more than one quarter of permafrost soil carbon in areas of continuous permafrost. We observe pervasive positive trends in vegetation productivity in areas of continuous permafrost, whereas areas underlain by discontinuous permafrost have proportionally less positive productivity trends and an increase in areas exhibiting negative productivity trends. Fire affects a much smaller proportion of the total area and thus a smaller amount of permafrost soil carbon, with the vast majority occurring in deciduous needleleaf forests. Our results indicate that vegetation productivity trends may be linked to permafrost distribution, fire affects a relatively small proportion of permafrost soil carbon, and Siberian larch forests will play a crucial role in the strength of the permafrost carbon climate feedback.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>arctic</keyword><keyword>boreal</keyword><keyword>ecosystem</keyword><keyword>fire</keyword><keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>This work is dedicated to the public domain under the Creative Commons Universal 1.0 Public Domain Dedication. To view a copy of this dedication, visit https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/.</para></intellectualRights><coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Northern Alaska and Russia, Arctic</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>156.7886</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>37.6173</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>71.2906</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>55.7558</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2016-01-01</calendarDate><time>01:01:01</time></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="1803559049124239"><individualName><givenName>Scott</givenName><surName>Mortensen</surName></individualName><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9663-2923</userId></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para>Soil organic carbon content to a depth of 1 m across the study region was quantified using the NCSCDv2 (NCSCDv2; Hugelius et al 2013). The NCSCDv2 represents a synthesis of multiple national and regional soil maps and pedon data, and is the source of the most recent and widely accepted estimates of organic carbon stored in permafrost soils. We chose to quantify organic carbon stocks in the upper 1 m because these near surface soils will be most affected by changes in ecosystem structure and disturbance regimes, and also because the 0–1 m data set is better constrained than deeper pools which are based upon fewer observations. The original dataset was in geographic coordinates on a 0.012° grid.</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>Variability in ecosystem types within the continuous and discontinuous permafrost zones were quantified using the Global Land Cover 2000 dataset (GLC2000; Bartholomé and Belward 2005). Percent tree canopy cover was mapped using the MODIS Vegetation Continuous Fields Collection 5.1 data product (MOD44B; Hansen et al 2003). We combined the 19 original GLC2000 land cover classes present in the study region into six aggregate classes for analysis. Aggregation of the land cover classes was informed by preliminary assessment of the spatial extent, percent canopy cover, other regional land cover products (Walker et al 2005, Sulla-Menashe et al 2011), and overall relevance to the study. Needleleaf deciduous and needleleaf evergreen classes were retained due to their extent and importance in the region, and all broadleaf or mixed leaf classes and burned forests were aggregated to an other forest class. These classes were aggregated because of their relatively small areal extents, and in the case of burned forests the dominant pre-fire vegetation type could not be determined. Mosaic forest and evergreen shrub were aggregated to the mosaic forest class. Evergreen shrub was included in this class because the two original classes were found in close proximity near latitudinal treeline (figure S1), and because the dominant shrub species in these systems are deciduous (e.g. Walker et al 2005). Moreover, the GLC2000 criteria for forest height is a minimum of 5 m, and it is likely that the evergreen shrub class consists of open woodlands with short slow-growing trees, and analysis of MODIS VCF data showed the evergreen shrub class to have a mean canopy cover of 16% (table 1), which is higher than the original mosaic forest class, and on par with needleleaf deciduous forests in the continuous permafrost zone. The remaining shrub and herbaceous classes were aggregated into the tundra class. Lastly, all non-vegetated classes that included any sort of management were aggregated into the other class. A summary of the classes is shown in table 1.</para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><description><para>The spatial domain for this study was defined using the Circum-Arctic Map of Permafrost and Ground Ice Conditions (CAMP; Brown et al 1998). This map covers the northern hemisphere poleward of 20° N latitude, and categorizes permafrost affected areas as continuous (90%–100% areal cover), discontinuous (50%–90% areal cover), sporadic (10%–50% areal cover), and intermittent (&lt;10% areal cover) permafrost zones. Our analyses were restricted to the continuous and discontinuous permafrost zones to avoid including large areas unaffected by permafrost. Because one of our aims was to quantify the amount of permafrost soil carbon underlying areas affected by fire and vegetation change within different ecosystems we further restricted our study area using the Northern Circumpolar Soil Carbon Database v2 (NCSCD; Hugelius et al 2013). This effectively removed altitudinal permafrost at lower latitudes (i.e. in the Alps and Himalayan mountain ranges). The final study domain included approximately 11 million km2 underlain by continuous permafrost and 3.5 million km2 with discontinuous permafrost (figure 1, table 1).</para></description></studyExtent><samplingDescription><para>Prior to analyses all data were transformed from native resolution and projection to Lambert Azimuthal Equal Area Projection (LAEA) with MODIS 500 m resolution. The 500 m spatial resolution was chosen to avoid loss or creation of data associated with resampling the MODIS burned area data. The MODIS Reprojection Tool (https://lpdaac.usgs.gov/tools/modis_reprojection_tool) was used to mosaic the monthly burned area product, reproject each file from sinusoidal to LAEA, and finally convert files to GeoTiff. These mosaics included data poleward of approximately 40° N latitude, and served as a template for resampling the remaining datasets. The CAMP, NCSCDv2, GLC2000, VCF, and GIMMS datasets were then reprojected and resampled to match the spatial extent and resolution of the burned area data set. The CAMP and GLC2000 include categorical variables and so were transformed using nearest neighbor resampling. The remaining maps included continuous variables and so were resampled using bilinear interpolation. All transformations were performed using the Raster package (Hijmans and van Etten 2013) in R.</para><para>Once all data were resampled to the common projection and spatial resolution the CAMP map was reclassified to exclude the sporadic and intermittent permafrost classes, and then masked to further exclude areas not covered by the NCSCDv2. Similarly, the NCSCDv2 was then masked using the modified CAMP map so that both maps covered the same area. We then masked the remaining data sets to include only data within the delineated study area (figure 1). The zonal function in the Raster package was used to quantify the distribution and variability in ecosystem structural and functional properties within the continuous and discontinuous permafrost zones, and also ecosystem structural and functional properties within vegetation zones.</para></samplingDescription></sampling></methods><project><title>NCEAS Data Science Training Exercise 1 - Reformatted Permafrost Dataset</title><personnel id="9849117188531624"><individualName><givenName>Scott</givenName><surName>Mortensen</surName></individualName><organizationName>NCEAS</organizationName><positionName>Data Science Fellow</positionName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel id="7167865392158215"><individualName><givenName>Michael</givenName><surName>Loranty</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel id="2252724920713003"><individualName><givenName>Wil</givenName><surName>Lieberman-Cribbin</surName></individualName><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><funding><para>NSF PLR grants 1623764, 1304040, 1304464, 1417700, 1417908, and 1417745. MML and WL-C received support from Colgate University and the Colgate University Research Council. LTB was supported by NASA Headquarters under the NASA Earth and Space Science Fellowship Program (grant NNX14AN65H) and by the ARCS Foundation Scholar Program.</para></funding></project><otherEntity><entityName>Reformatted_Permafrost_dataset (1).csv</entityName><entityDescription>This is a training dataset from the NCEAS data science fellowship training. Exercise 1.</entityDescription><entityType>text/csv</entityType></otherEntity></dataset></eml:eml>